# Ernest Toochukwu Samuel

### **Mechatronics Engineer**

I am a diligent and versatile engineer pursuing a MAS/MSc in Mechatronics Engineering. I hold a B.Engr. in Mechanical Engineering and have gained valuable work experience in the renewable energy industry, construction, and information and communication technology (ICT). I have a strong interest in sustainable technology. I am skilled in computer programming (Python, C++, MATLAB, HTML and PLC), energy audit, solar PV installation, leadership, emotional intelligence, CAD design, mathematical and engineering analysis, cash flow management, critical thinking, and problem-solving. With a passion for data analysis and machine learning, I am committed to utilising my skills and experience to drive innovation in sustainable development and make a meaningful impact on society.

#### Contact

samuelernest91@gmail .com







### **Education**

## MSC. MECHATRONICS ENGINEERING

Ashesi University, Ghana January 2023 – Present

Control Systems,
International
Environmental
Politics, Leading
Teams, Renewable
Energy Technologies,
Machine Learning,
Manufacturing
Processes, Systems
Identification and
Modeling, Robotics
and Mechatronics,
Investment appraisal
and cost-effectiveness
analysis / Corporate

### **Experience**

#### FINANCE AND SPONSORSHIP MANAGEMENT

TEDXASHESIUNIVERSITY, ACCRA, GHANA September 2022 – May 2023

- Curated and Managed budget.
- Sourced for funds and sponsorship to raise equal or more than the budgeted amount.
- Analysed and Managed Cash flow internally and externally.

### **OPERATIONS AND MAINTENANCE ENGINEER**

ICE COMMERCIAL POWER, DELTA STATE, NIGERIA January 2021 – January 2022

I Ensured daily Operations and maintenance of ten mini-grid solar plant sites in Asaba, Delta State, Nigeria.

• Troubleshooted, Maintained, Changed, and Installed smart meters

Responsibilities and sustainability, Energy Systems and Mobility, Process Engineering, Systems Identification and Modelling, Advanced Communication Systems and Internet of Things, Development Economics, Sustainable Engineering, Product Development and Reliability and Risk

## MAS. MECHATRONICS ENGINEERING

ETH Zurich, Switzerland January 2022 - Present

Mathematical Tools, Thermofluids, Computer Programming and Embedded Systems, Analog and Digital Electronics, Statics and Solid Mechanics, Signals and Systems, Material Engineering, Dynamics and Computational Methods

# B. ENGR MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

University of Nigeria, Nigeria October 2014 – September 2019

Grade: 4.18/5

- Monitored all sites on two independent Software UI and resolved any observed issues within the shortest possible time.
- Designed, installed, and maintained Solar PV systems.
- Collated daily Energy generation and consumption data
- Detailed daily reporting to the Regional Operations Manager through Google Sheets, forms, and email.
- Carried out monthly and weekly data analysis and presentation of site performance with improvement and optimisation suggestions

#### **MECHANICAL ENGINEERING INTERN**

FEROTEX CONSTRUCTION COMPANY, ENUGU STATE, NIGERIA April 2018 – October 2018

- Assisted in Heavy-duty machinery (Caterpillar machines and Trucks) servicing and maintenance.
- Managed spare parts Inventories, diesel, and engine oil usage daily.
- Reported to the Head of the mechanical department.

# INFORMATION AND COMMUNICATION TECHNOLOGY INTERN UNIVERSITY OF NIGERIA ICT UNIT, ENUGU STATE NIGERIA

July 2017 - September 2017

July 2016 - September 2016

- Designed and managed Google forms for e-documentation
- Carried out WIFI connectivity monitoring and downtime optimization protocols by reporting to the management.
- Transformed and uploaded physical files into e-records using Microsoft Suits, for Department of Education Foundation.

### **Skills**

CAD Design: NX and Autodesk Inventor.

Troubleshooting:

Mechanical and

Electrical.

Teamwork.

Programming: Python, C++, MATLAB, HTML and PLC.

Data Analyst and Machine Learning.

Cash Flow Management and Analytics

Microsoft Office

Creativity Technique.

Problem-Solving and Critical Thinking.

Emotional Intelligence

Energy Audit and Storage Design.

Electrical Connections.

Solar PV System Design and Installation.

### **Leadership Skills**

**ISA VICE PRESIDENT** INTERNATIONAL STUDENTS' ASSOCIATION, ASHESI UNIVERSITY, GHANA
September 2022 – Present

ARM\_Y CLUB VICE PRESIDENT ARM ENGAGE STUDENT CLUB,

ASHESI UNIVERSITY, GHANA

August 2022 - Present

**PLATOON LEADER NYSC** BATCH B STREAM 1, RIVERS STATE CAMP, NIGERIA

November 2020 - October 2021

**ENGINEERING DESIGN GROUP LEADER** MECHANICAL ENGINEERING DESIGN PROJECT, UNN, NIGERIA

ME511 Group six, 2019

### **Courses and Certifications**

**SOFT-SKILLS TRAINING,** JOBBER MAN (COUSERA COURSE) March 2021

PYTHON FOR DATA SCIENCE, DATAQUEST

August 2021

ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE, IBM DIGITAL - NATION

(EXPLORER AWARD AND V2)

April 2020

**ENERGY TRANSITION; INNOVATION TOWARDS A LOW-CARBON FUTURE, IFP SCHOOL** 

April 2021

**SOLAR PV SYSTEMS,** ENERGY TALENT COMPANY

July 2020

**AUTODESK INVENTOR, LINKEDIN LEARNING** 

May 2022

THE COSHH RISK ASSESSOR CERTIFICATION, THE KNIGHTS OF

SAFETY ACADEMY

October 2019

### Volunteering

**MATHEMATICS TEACHER,** NATIONAL YOUTHS SERVICE CORP, PORT HARCOURT, NIGERIA

November 2020 - October 2021

#### References

Available upon request.